So, we need to build an app that adapts well to
all different devices. But there's so many types of devices. So,
where do we begin? Well, we can start by grouping them
into buckets based on physical size. We can have a bucket for
phones and a bucket for seven inch tablets. And a bucket
for ten inch tablets as well. You can go even more granular
based on screen width. But these are the most common buckets
that you'll need. Now, classifying based on size alone is not enough.
Even among devices of the same size, there's still
a wide range of screen densities. Screen density is calculated
from the number of dots per inch on the device
or DPI. Scale starts off with low density devices, also
known as LDPI devices. It has about 120 dots
per inch, then it increases to medium density, high density
all the way to extra, extra, extra high density devices
were the number of dots per inch is much higher.
So, how do we build an app that accounts for
all these different screen densities? Well, when we specify layout dimensions,
we quickly realize that we can't use pixels. For example,
a 48 pixel button that looks fine on an MDPI device
will look much smaller on a higher density device where
the pixels are more compacted and the physical size of 48
pixels is much smaller. The user wants a button to be
easily tappable, and so it shouldn't change based on screen density.
So we need a consistent unit of measure to define physical
size, and in Android we call that density-independent pixels or dips
or dp for short. That way, a 48 dp button will
be the same physical size across all these different screen densities.